Guide to the Julius Logan Brasher Papers, 1935-2012 and undated RL.11268
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Julius Logan Brasher papers
1935-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Brasher, Julius Logan, 1914-2012
RL.11268
12.5 Linear Feet
Collection spans the pastoral career of United Methodist minister Julius Logan Brasher. Brasher was minister at six congregations in New Jersey from the early 1940s to 1976, when he and his wife Lois Brasher relocated to the Brasher home of Gadsden, Alabama. Collection contains Brasher's diaries and pastor's record books, materials from the churches where he ministered, sermons and accompanying notes, subject and name files, correspondence, photographs, and printed materials.
Biographical / Historical
Julius Logan Brasher (1914-2012) was a Methodist minister in New Jersey and Alabama. The son of fellow minister John Lakin Brasher, Julius Brasher graduated from Drew Seminary in 1937. Brasher served as a minister at United Methodist churches in New Jersey from 1937 to 1976. In 1976, he and his wife Lois returned to his hometown of Gadsden, Alabama, where he served as pastoral adviser and teacher until 2011.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Julius Logan Brasher Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Related Materials
The Rubenstein Library also holds the John Lakin Brasher Papers, who was the father of Julius Logan Brasher, and the Boatman Family Papers.
Collection Overview
The Julius Logan Brasher Papers document the personal and pastoral life of the Methodist minister. Son of Holiness Movement minister John Lakin Brasher, Julius Logan Brasher attended Drew Theological School. He served as a Methodist minister in New Jersey from 1937 to 1976, after which time he retired to his original home of Gadsden, Alabama. He continued to serve as a pastor and religious advisor in that community through 2011. Brasher's activities as a minister at six churches in New Jersey and two in Alabama are documented throughout the collection. Collection contains Brasher's diaries and record books, sermon notes, church files, name and subject files, correspondence, photographs, some printed materials, and one audiotape.
Diaries files comprise diaries, calendars, and pastor's record books kept by Brasher between 1946 and 1977. Entries contain notes about parishioners, appointments, and sermons given.
The sermons and religious writings files contain full-length sermons as well as notes and cue cards used by Brasher to give sermons at churches throughout his career, including his years as a student at Drew Theological School. Topics range from weekly Sunday services to weddings, memorials, and holidays. Some sermon notes are folded into the church program during which the sermon was given. Many sermons are undated. Other writings include some of Brasher's academic papers from Seminary as well as narrative religious writings from throughout his career. A portion of the sermons arrived alphabetically sorted by Brasher, referring to the titles of the sermons.
The Churches files relate to Brasher's activities as a pastor at United Methodist churches in New Jersey and Alabama. The files contain church programs, newsletters, correspondence, and printed materials collected and created by Brasher. Files from Gadsden UMC include memos and notes from the Julius Brasher Discussion Class. The following churches are represented in the series: • First Congregational Church of Chester, NJ (Chester, NJ): 1939-1942 • Blairstown United Methodist Church (Blairstown, NJ): 1942-1946 • Denville Community Church (United Methodist) (Denville, NJ): 1946-1955 • Rutherford United Methodist Church (Rutherford, NJ): 1955-1962 • Westwood United Methodist Church (Westwood, NJ): 1962-1968 • Plainfield United Methodist Church (Plainfield, NJ): 1972-1976 • Walnut Grove United Methodist Church (Walnut Grove, AL): 1978-1979 • Gadsden United Methodist Church (Gadsden, AL): 1979-2011
Correspondence files contain letters received by Brasher beginning with his tenure at Drew Seminary and throughout his career. Primary among the correspondents is his father, John Lakin Brasher. The elder Brasher wrote letters to Julius and the rest of the family several times a week from the 1930s through the 1950s. Other correspondents include parishioners, friends, and other family members. Name and Subject Files contain correspondence, printed materials, notes, and writings on subjects assigned by Brasher. Among the name files is a folder with Brasher's correspondence with Bishop G. Bromley Oxnam, a social reformer and Methodist Bishop. Oxnam was accused of being a communist by Donald Jackson. Some correspondence relates to these accusations, and Brasher's support of Oxnam. Subject files include Brasher's files from Drew Theological School, the Rotary Club, the Northern New Jersey Cabinet, and his work on the Board of Education trustees and the Board of Discipleship Trustees.
Photographs are mostly undated black-and-white snapshots from Brasher's church communities in New Jersey. Common subjects are Sunday school classes, church picnics, headshots of congregants, and promotional images of the churches where Brasher was pastor.
United Methodist Church (U.S.); Clergy -- Diaries; Methodist Church -- Sermons -- 20th century; Black-and-white prints (photographs); Alabama -- Religious life and customs; New Jersey -- Religious life and customs; Brasher, John Lakin, 1868-1971; Drew Theological Seminary; Oxnam, G. Bromley (Garfield Bromley), 1891-1963
- Diaries, 1946-1977; 12 folders (Box 1)
- Sermons and Religious Writings, 1937-1990s and undated; 33 folders (Box 1, Box 2, Box 6)
- Sermons and Religious Writings; Easter and Christmas/Life of Christ, 1950s - 1970s; 3 folders (Box 6)
- Sermons and Religious Writings; Subjects: A - E, 1950s - 1970s; 13 folders (Box 7)
- Sermons and Religious Writings; Subjects: F - I, 1950s - 1970s; 13 folders (Box 8)
- Sermons and Religious Writings; Subjects: J - P, 1950s - 1970s; 15 folders (Box 9)
- Sermons and Religious Writings; Subjects: P - Y, 1950s - 1970s; 16 folders (Box 10)
- Churches, 1940-1979; 32 folders (Box 3)
- Subject and Name Files, undated; 36 folders (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1935-2011; 10 folders (Box 4)
- Photographs, undated; 5 folders (Box 5, Oversize-folder 1)
- Printed Materials, 1936-1937 (Box 5)
  Scope and Contents
  Issues of the official student weekly of Asbury University, the Asbury Collegian, 1936-1937.
- Audiovisual Materials, 1966; 1 tapes (Box 5, Tape RL11268-CS-0001)
  One audiotape from Westwood United Methodist Church, 1966.
- Class Notes; High School and Asbury, 1950's - 1970's; 2 folders (Box 6)
- N. New Jersey Conference directory, 1967 (Box 6)